(upbeat orchestral music)
(babies crying)
(chisel pounding)
(whistling)
(tongue clicking)
- Yeah, D.B.
Oh, just cleaning out the deadwood.
Okay.
- Look, Mr. Connell, I just can't afford
to be without work right
now, not even for a day.
I've got a mother and two kid sisters to--
- [Secretary] More good luck telegrams.
- Well, you know how it is.
I've just got to keep on working, see?
- Sorry, sister, I was sent
down here to clean house.
I told you, I can't use
your column anymore.
It's lavender and old lace.
- Sir?
- Send those other people in.
- I'll tell you what I'll do.
I get $30.
I'll take $25, $20 if necessary.
I'll do anything you say.
- It isn't the money.
We're after circulation.
What we need is fireworks,
people who can hit with
sledgehammers, start arguments.
- Oh, I can do that.
I know this town inside-out.
Oh, give me a chance, please.
- All right, come in, come in, come in.
Cashier's got your check.
Who are these people?
Gibbs, Crawley, Cunningham, Giles
Hey you, sister.
Don't forget to get out your last column
before you pick up your check.
(door slamming)
(trashcan clattering)
- You're a couple of sticks
shy in your column, Ann.
- Big, rich slob like
D.B. Norton buys a paper
and 40 heads are chopped off.
- Did you get it, too?
- Yeah.
You too?
Oh, Joe.
Oh, I'm sorry darling.
Why don't we tear the building down?
- Before you do, Ann,
perhaps you'd better finish this column.
- Yeah, lavender and old lace.
Wait, Joe.
Wait.
He wants fireworks, huh?
Okay.
(typewriter keys clacking)
Here.
- Below is a letter which
reached my desk this morning.
It's a commentary on what we
laughingly call a civilized world.
Dear Miss Mitchell, four years ago,
I was fired outta my job.
Since then, I haven't been
able to get another one.
At first I was sore at
the state administration
because it's on account
of the slimy politics here
we have all this unemployment.
But in looking around,
it seems the whole world's going to pot.
So, in protest, I'm
going to commit suicide
by jumping off the City Hall roof.
Signed, a disgusted
American citizen, John Doe.
Editor's note, if you ask this column,
the wrong people are
jumping off the roofs.
Hey, Ann, this is the
old fak-a-roo, isn't it?
- Nevermind that, Joe, go ahead.
(laughing)
(chattering)
(glass shattering)
(workers laughing)
- And it's because of the slimy politics
that we have all this unemployment here.
There it is.
That's D.B. Norton's opening
attack on the governor.
- Why, Jim, it's just a
letter sent into a column.
- No, no, I can smell it, that's Norton.
- [Governor] Good morning, gentlemen.
- Good morning, Governor.
- [Governor] You're here rather early.
- Governor, did you happen to
see this in the New Bulletin?
- Yes.
I had it served with my
breakfast this morning.
- Jim thinks it's D.B. Norton at work.
- Of course it is.
- Oh, come, Jim.
That little item?
D.B. Norton does things
in a much bigger way.
- {Jim] This is his opening
attack on you, Governor,
take my word for it.
What did he buy a paper for?
Why did he engage a high-pressure
editor like Connell for?
He's in the oil business.
I tell you, Governor,
he's after your scalp.
- All right, Jim, all right,
don't burst a blood vessel.
I'll look into it.
- [Secretary] Yes sir?
- Get me Spencer of the
Daily Chronicle please.
- Yes, yes, I saw it, Governor.
If you ask me, that's a phony letter.
Why, that gag has got whiskers on it.
Hmm?
Okay, I'll get the mayor
and maybe the Chamber of
Commerce to go after them.
Get Mayor Lovett on the phone.
- Sorry, the mayor's
busy on the other phone.
- Yes, I know, Mrs. Brewster.
It's a terrible reflection on our city.
I've had a dozen calls already.
- [Man] Spencer at the Chronicle.
- Hold him.
- Just a minute.
- Yes, Mrs. Brewster, I'm listening.
- I insist that this John Doe man be found
and given a job at once.
Now, if something isn't done about it,
I'll call out the whole auxiliary.
and the junior auxiliary.
We'll hold a meeting and see that--
- Yes, Spency?
Who?
The governor?
Well, what about me?
It's my building he's jumping off of,
and I'm up for reelection too.
(shushing)
What are you doing?
Get Connell at the Bulletin.
Why, he's liable to go right past my--
- Get me Connell.
- What was that?
- What?
- Out the window.
Something just flew by.
- I didn't see anything.
- Well, don't stand there,
you idiot, go and look.
Open the window.
Oh, why did he have to
pick on my building?
Is there a crowd in the street?
- No, sir.
- Then maybe he's caught
on a ledge, look again.
- I think it must've been a seagull.
- A seagull?
What's a seagull doing
around the City Hall?
That's a bad omen, isn't it?
- Oh, no sir, the
seagull is a lovely bird.
- It's all right, Mrs.
Brewster, it was just a seagull.
- Connell?
- Nothing's happened yet.
No, I'm watching.
Don't worry, Mrs. Brewster.
Just leave it all to me.
Spencer, I'll call you back.
Hello, Connell?
This is--
What are you doing?
This is the mayor.
- Yes, Mayor Lovett.
How many times are you gonna call me?
I've got everybody and his brother
and sister out looking for him.
Did you see the box I'm running?
An appeal to John Doe.
Think it over, John.
Life can be beautiful, says mayor.
If you need a job, apply
to editor to this paper,
and so forth and so forth.
Okay, Mayor, I'll let you know
as soon as I have something.
What?
Well, pull down the blinds.
- Went up to Miss Mitchell's house, boss.
Boy, she's in a bad way.
- Where is she?
- Hey, do you know something?
She supports her mother and two kids.
What do you know about that?
- Did you find her?
- No.
Her mother's awful worried about her.
When she left the house,
said she was going on a roaring drunk.
The girl, I mean.
- Go out and find her.
- Sure.
(phone ringing)
Hey, but the biggest
thing I didn't tell you.
Her old man's Doc Mitchell.
- Hello?
- You know, the doc that
saved my mother's life
and wouldn't take any money for it?
You remember that?
Okay, boss, I'll go and look for her.
(clanging)
- Holy smokes, Commissioner,
you've had 24 hours.
Okay, Hawkshaw, grab a
pencil, here it is again.
About five foot five, brown
eyes, light chestnut hair,
and as fine a pair of legs as
ever walked into this office.
- Did you wanna see me?
- No, I've had the whole Army
and Navy out searching for you
because that's a game
we play here every day.
- I remember distinctly being fired.
- That's right.
But you have a piece of property
that still belongs to this newspaper
and I'd like to have it.
- What's that?
- The letter.
- What letter?
- The letter from John Doe.
- Oh.
- [Henry] The whole town's in an uproar.
We've gotta find him and
the letter's the only clue.
- There is no letter.
- We'll get a handwriting expert to--
What?
- There is no letter.
- Say that again.
- There's no letter, I made it up.
- You made it up?
- Mm-hmm.
You said you wanted fireworks.
- Don't you know there are
nine jobs waiting for this guy,
22 families wanna board him free,
five women wanna marry him,
and the mayor's practically
ready to adopt him?
And you--
- Just called the morgue, boss.
They say there's a girl there--
- [Henry] Shut up.
- Ann.
Say, why didn't you--
- Beany.
- Only one thing to do, Hank,
drop the whole business quickly.
- How?
- Run a story.
Say John Doe was in here and
he's sorry he wrote the letter.
- That's right.
You got it, sure.
He came in here and I
let him change his mind.
Bulletin editor saves John Doe's life.
Why, it's perfect.
I'll have Ned write it up.
Oh, Ned?
I've got a story I want you to--
- Wait a minute.
Listen, you great big wonderful
genius of a newspaper man.
You came down here to shoot some life
into this dying paper, didn't you?
Well, the whole town's
curious about John Doe,
and, boom, just like that,
you're going to bury him.
There's enough circulation in that man
to start a shortage in the ink market.
- In what man?
- John Doe.
- What John Doe?
- Our John Doe, the one I made up.
Look, genius, now look.
Suppose there was a John Doe
and he walked into this office.
What would you do?
Find him a job and forget about
the whole business, I suppose, huh?
Not me.
I'd make a deal.
- A deal?
- Sure, when you get ahold
of a stunt that sells papers,
you don't drop it like a hot potato.
Why, this is good for at
least a couple of months.
You know what I'd do?
Between now and let's say
Christmas when he's gonna jump,
I'd run a daily yarn,
starting with his boyhood,
his schooling, his first job.
A wide-eyed youngster
facing a chaotic world.
The problem of the average man,
of all the John Does in the world.
Now, then comes the drama.
He meets discouragement.
He finds the world has feet of clay.
His ideals crumble.
So what does he do?
He decides to commit suicide in protest
against the state of civilization.
He thinks of the river.
But no, no, he has a better idea.
The City Hall.
Why?
Because he wants to attract attention.
He wants to get a few
things off his chest,
and that's the only way
he can get himself heard.
- So?
So he writes me a letter and I dig him up.
He pours out his soul to me.
And from now on, we quote,
I protest, by John Doe.
He protests against all
the evils in the world,
the greed, the lust, the hate, the fear,
all of man's inhumanity to man.
Arguments will start.
Should he commit suicide or should he not?
People will write in pleading with him.
But no.
No, sir.
John Doe will remain adamant.
On Christmas Eve, hot or cold, he goes.
See?
- Very pretty.
Very pretty indeed, Miss Mitchell.
But would you mind telling
me who goes on Christmas Eve?
- John Doe.
- What John Doe?.
- The one we hire for
the job, you lunkhead.
- Wait a minute, wait a minute.
Let me get this through
this lame brain of mine.
Are you suggesting we
go out and hire someone
to say he's gonna commit
suicide on Christmas Eve?
Is that it?
- Why, you're catching on.
- Who, for instance?
- Anybody.
Beany'll do.
- Why, sure--
Who, me?
Jump off a--
Oh, no.
Any time but Christmas, I'm superstitious.
(clanging)
(sighing)
- Miss Mitchell, do me a favor, will you?
Go on out and get married
and have a lotta babies,
but stay outta newspaper business.
- [Man] Better get that story
in, Hank, it's getting late.
- You're supposed to be a smart guy.
If it was raining $100 bills,
you'd be out looking for
a dime you lost someplace.
- Holy smokes, wasting my time
listening to this mad woman.
- [Ned] Look, Chief.
Look what the Chronicle's
running on John Doe.
They say it's a fake.
- Why, the no good--
John Doe story amateur journalism.
It's palpably phony.
It's a wonder anyone
is taking it seriously.
What do you think of those guys?
- That's fine, that's fine.
Now, fall right into their lap.
Go ahead, say John Doe walked in
and called the whole thing off.
You know what that's gonna
sound like on top of this.
- That's all, Ned, thank you.
- All right.
- Amateur journalism, huh?
Why, that bunch of sophomores.
I can teach them more about--
- Hey, boss, get a load of this.
- What?
- Look.
- [Henry] What do they want?
- [Beany] They all say they
wrote the John Doe letter.
(talking over each other)
- Oh, they all wrote the letter.
- Tell them all to wait.
Look, Mr. Connell, one of
those men is your John Doe.
They're desperate and will do
anything for a cup of coffee.
Pick one out and you can make
the chronicle eat their words.
- I'm beginning to like this.
- If you ask me, Hank, you're
playing around with dynamite.
- No, no, no, no, no, the gal's right.
We can't let the Chronicle
get the laugh on us.
We've gotta produce a John Doe now.
Amateur journalism, huh?
I'll show those guys.
- Sure, and there's no reason
for them to find out the truth either
because, naturally, I won't say anything.
- Okay, sister, you get your job back.
- Plus a bonus.
- What bonus?
- Oh, the bonus of $1,000 the
Chronicle was going to pay me
for this little document.
You'll find that it says that,
I, Ann Mitchell, hereby certify
that the John Doe letter
was created by me--
- I can read, I can read.
- Sorry.
- You think this is worth $1,000, do you?
- Oh, the Chronicle would
consider it dirt cheap.
- Packs everything, including a gun.
Okay, sister, you got yourself a deal.
Now, let's take a look at the candidates.
The one we pick has gotta
be the typical average man,
typical American that
can keep his mouth shut.
- Show me an American who can
keep his mouth shut and I'll eat him.
- Okay, Beany, bring 'em in one at a time.
(angry chattering)
(whimsical big band music)
Did you write that
letter to Miss Mitchell?
- No, I didn't.
- What are you doin' up here then?
- Well, the paper said there
were some jobs around loose.
Thought there might be one left over.
- Had any schooling?
- Yeah, a little.
- What do you do when you work?
- I used to pitch.
- Baseball?
- Yeah, till my wing went bad.
- Where'd you play?
- Bush leagues, mostly.
- How about family, got any family?
- No.
- Oh, just traveling through, huh?
- Yep, me and a friend of mine.
He's outside.
- Looks all right.
- He's perfect, a baseball player.
What could be more American?
- [Henry] Wish he had a family though.
- [Man] Be less complicated
without a family.
- Look at that face, it's wonderful.
They'll believe him.
Come on.
- [Henry] What's your name?
- Willoughby, John Willoughby.
Long John Willoughby they
called me in baseball.
- Would you like to make some money?
- Yeah, maybe.
- Would you be willing to say you wrote
that letter and stick by it?
- I get the idea.
Yeah, maybe.
- That's our man, he's made to order.
- [Henry] I don't know,
he don't seem like the kind of a guy
that would fall in line.
- When you're desperate for money,
you do a lotta things, Mr. Connell.
He's our man, I tell you.
He's fainted!
Get some water, quickly.
- [Henry] Hurry up, Pop.
Why don't you sit down?
- Are you all right?
- Yeah, I'm all right.
- How many is that, six?
Pretty hungry, weren't you?
- [Man] Say all this John Doe
business is batty if you ask me.
- Well, nobody asked you.
- Trying to improve the world
by jumping off buildings.
You couldn't improve the world
if the buildings jumped on you.
- Don't mind the Colonel, he hates people.
- [Ann] He likes you well
enough to stick around.
- Oh, that's 'cause we
both play doohickeys.
I met him in a boxcar
a couple of years ago.
I was fooling around with my harmonica,
and he comes over and joins in.
I haven't been able to shake him since.
(harmonica music)
("William Tell Overture" by
Gioachino Rossini on harmonicas)
- All right, boys, here he is.
- No, no, no, you can't take
pictures of him like that,
eating a sandwich and with a beard.
- But he's gonna jump off a building.
- Yes, but not because he's out of a job.
That's not news.
This man's going to jump
as a matter of principle.
- Maybe you're right.
- We'll clean him up
and put him a hotel
room, under bodyguards.
We'll make a mystery out of him.
- Do you speak to Mr. Norton?
- Thinks it's terrific.
Says for us to go the limit.
Wants us to build a bonfire
under every big shot in the state.
- Oh, swell, is that the contract?
- Yes.
What's he doing here?
- Friend of his.
They play duets together.
- Duets?
But can we trust him?
- Oh.
- I trust him.
- Oh, you trust him, eh?
Well, that's fine.
I suppose he trusts you, too?
- [Ann] Oh, stop worrying.
He's all right.
- Well, okay, but we don't want more
than a couple of hundred
people in on this thing.
Now, the first thing I
want is an exact copy
of the John Doe letter
in your own handwriting.
- I got it all ready, here.
- Now, that's fine.
Now, I want you to sign this agreement.
It gives us an exclusive
story under your name
day by day from now until Christmas.
On December 26th you get one
railroad ticket out of town,
and the Bulletin agrees to
pay to have your arm fixed.
That's what you want, isn't it?
- Yeah, but it's got to
be by Bone-Setter Brown.
- Okay, Bone-Setter Brown goes.
Here, sign it.
Meanwhile, here's $50 for spending money.
That's fine.
Beany?
- Yes, boss?
- Take charge of him.
Get him a suite at the Imperial
and hire some bodyguards.
- Yeah, and some new clothes, Beany.
- [Beany] Do you think we
better have him deloused?
- [Henry] Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- [Beany] Both of 'em?
- [Henry] Yes, both of 'em.
But don't let 'em out of your sight.
- Hey, Beany, gray suit, huh?
- Yeah.
- Okay, fellas.
And you, start pounding that typewriter.
Oh boy, this is terrific.
No responsibilities on our part.
Just statements from John Doe
and we can blast our heads off.
- Before you pop too many buttons,
don't forget to make out
that check for 1,000.
(groaning)
- Okay fellas, now let me see.
You sit outside the door.
Nobody comes in, see.
You two fellas sit in here.
- Hey, pretty nifty, huh?
- You ain't gonna get me to stay here.
- [Beany] Sure you are.
- No sir, that spot under the bridge
where we slept last
night's good enough for me.
- Hey, what do I do with this baggage?
- [Beany] Oh, stick 'em in the bedroom.
- Give me mine, I ain't stayin'.
You know, we were headed for
the Columbia River country
before all this John Doe business came up.
You remember that, don't you?
- Sure, I remember.
- Say, did your ears pop
coming up in the elevator?
Mine did.
- Oh, Long John, I tell ya, it's no good.
You're gonna get used to a lotta stuff
that's gonna wreck you.
Why, that $50 in your pocket's
beginning to show up on you already.
(harmonica music)
And don't pull that on me neither.
- Stop worrying, Colonel.
I'm gonna get my arm fixed outta this.
- Hey, here's some
cigars the boss sent us.
Have one.
- Hey, cigars.
- Help yourself.
- No.
- Hey, I'll bet ya even the Major Leaguers
don't rate an outfit like this.
- [Man] Here, make yourself comfortable.
Paper?
- No, I don't read no papers
and I don't listen to radios either.
I know the world's been
shaved by a drunken barber
and I don't have to read it.
I've seen guys like you go under before.
Guys that never had a worry,
then they got ahold of
some dough and went goofy.
The first thing that happens to a guy--
- [Beany] Hey, did you
get a load of the bedroom?
- No.
- The first thing that
happens to a guy like that,
he starts wanting to go into restaurants
and sit down at a table and eat
salads and cupcakes and tea.
Boy, what that kinda
food does to your system.
The next thing the dope wants is a room.
Yes sir, a room with steam
heat, and curtains and rugs.
And before you know it,
he's all softened up
and he can't sleep unless he has a bed.
- Hey, stop worrying, Colonel.
50 bucks ain't gonna ruin me.
- I've seen plenty of fellas
start out with 50 bucks
and wind up with a bank account.
- Hey, what's a matter
with a bank account anyway?
- You let me tell you, Long John,
when you become a guy with
a bank account, they gotcha.
Yes sir, they gotcha.
- Who's got him?
- The heelots.
- Who?
- Hey, there's the City Hall tower
I'm supposed to jump off of.
It's even higher than this.
- Who's got him?
- The heelots.
- [John Doe] Woo.
- Hey, wait a minute.
You're not supposed to
jump till Christmas Eve.
Do you wanna get me in a jam?.
- If it's gonna get you in
a jam, I'll do you a favor.
I won't jump.
- And when they got you,
you got no more chance than a road rabbit.
- Hey, who'd you say was gonna get him?
- Say, is this one of those places
where you ring if you want something?
- Yeah, yeah, just use the phone.
- Boy, I've always wanted to do this.
- Hey, Doc, look.
Look, Doc.
Gimme that again, will ya?
Who's gonna get him?
- The heelots.
- Who are they?
- Listen, sucker, you ever been broke?
- Sure, mostly often.
- All right.
You're walking along, not
a nickel in your jeans,
you're free as the wind,
nobody bothers you.
Hundreds of people pass you
by in every line of business,
shoes, hats, automobiles,
radios, furniture, everything.
They're all nice lovable
people and they let you alone.
Is that right?
Then you get ahold of some
dough and what happens?
All those nice, sweet,
lovable people become heelots.
A lotta heels.
They begin creeping up on you,
trying to sell you something.
They got long claws and they
get a stranglehold on you.
And you squirm and you duck and you holler
and you try to push 'em away,
but you haven't got a
chance, they've got you.
First thing you know, you own things.
A car, for instance.
Now your whole life is messed up
with a lot more stuff.
You got license fees and number plates
and gas and oil and taxes and insurance
and identification cards and letters
and bills and flat tires and
dents and traffic tickets
and motorcycle cops and
courtrooms and lawyers and fines
and a-million-and-one other things.
Then what happens?
You're not the free and
happy guy you used to be.
You gotta have money to
pay for all those things.
So, you go after what
the other fella's got.
And there you are,
you're a heelot yourself.
- You win, Colonel, here, take the 50.
Go out and get rid of it.
- You bet I will, just as fast as I can.
I'm gonna get some canned
goods, a fishing rod,
and the rest I'm gonna give away.
- Give away?
- Hey, get me a pitcher's glove.
I gotta get me some practice.
- Say, he's giving it away,
I'm gonna get me some of that.
- Hey, come back here, you heelot.
- Will you send up five
hamburgers with all the trimmings,
five chocolate ice cream sodas,
and five pieces of apple pie?
No, apple, with cheese.
Yeah, thanks.
- Hello there.
Well, if it isn't the man about town.
- All set, Miss Ann?
- Hmm?
Oh, oh yes, let's go.
Let's see, we want some
action in these pictures.
- Action?
- Mm-hmm.
- That's good.
- No, no, no.
This man's going to jump off a roof.
Here, wait a minute,
let me comb your hair.
Sit down.
There, that's better.
You know, he's got a nice face, hasn't he?
- Yeah, he's pretty. (laughing)
- Here, sit down.
Quiet, egghead.
All right, now a serious expression.
- I can't, I'm feeling too good.
- [Ann] Oh, come on now, this is serious.
You're a man disgusted
with all of civilization.
- With all of it?
- [Ann] Yes, you're sore
at the world, come on now.
- Oh, crabby guy, huh?
- Yeah.
No, no.
No. (laughing)
No, look.
You don't have to smell the world.
(laughing)
- With all those guys
in the bleachers think--
- Nevermind those guys.
All right, stand up.
Now, let's see what you
look like when you protest.
- Against what?
- [Ann] Against anything, just protest.
- You got me.
- Oh, look, I'm the umpire
and you just cut the heart of
the plate with your fast one
and I called it a ball.
What would you do?
- Oh you did, huh?
- [Ann] Yeah.
- Why can't you call 'em right,
you boneheaded big-eared--
- [Ann] Grab it, Eddie, grab it.
(big band music)
- [Newspaper Man] Extra, extra!
(chattering)
Extra.
Extra, extra!
(chattering)
- I don't care whose
picture they're publishing.
I still say that this
John Doe person is a myth,
and you can quote me on that.
And I'm going to insist
on his being produced for questioning.
You know as well as I
do that this whole thing
is being engineered by a vicious man
with a vicious purpose, Mr. D.B. Norton.
(whistle blowing)
(engines revving)
- Mr. Connell and Miss
Mitchell are at the house, sir.
- Oh, they are?
All right, come on.
- Personally, I think it's just
plain stupidity to drop it now.
You should see his fan mail, thousands.
Why, it's going over like a house afire.
- What are you afraid of, Connell?
It's doubled our circulation.
- Yeah, but it's got everybody sore.
Ads are being pulled.
The governor's starting a libel suit.
What's more, they all
know John Doe's a phony,
and they insist on seeing him.
- Well, what about it?
Let them see him.
We'll go 'em one better,
they can also hear him.
You own a radio station, Mr. Norton.
Why not put him on the air?
- Watch out for this dame,
D.B., she'll drive you batty.
- Oh--
- Look, we can't let 'em
get to this bush-league
pitcher and start pumping him.
Good night.
No telling what that screwball might do.
I walked in yesterday, here he is,
standing on a table with a
fishing pole, fly-casting.
Take my advice and get him outta town
before this thing explodes in our faces.
- If you do, Mr. Norton,
you're just as much of
a dumb cluck as he is.
Excuse me.
- No, you've got yourself a meal ticket
and you hate to let go.
- Sure, it's a meal
ticket for me, I admit it.
But it's also a windfall
for somebody like Mr. Norton
who's trying to crash national politics.
That's what you bought the
newspaper for, isn't it?
You wanna reach a lotta people, don't you?
Well, put John Doe on the air
and you can reach 130 million of 'em.
He can say anything he wants
and they'll listen to him.
All right, we'll forget
the Governor and the Mayor
and all the small fry like that.
This can arouse national interest.
If he made a hit around here,
he can do it everyplace
else in the country.
And you'll be pulling
the strings, Mr. Norton.
- Go down to the office and
arrange for some radio time.
- Why, D.B., you're not gonna fall--
- I want it as soon as possible.
- Okay.
I just came in to get warm, myself.
Come on, let's go.
- Don't you go.
I wanna talk to you.
Sit down.
Hey, this John Doe idea was yours, huh?
- Yes sir.
- How much money do you get?
- $30.
Well then, what are you after?
I mean what do you want,
a journalistic career?
- Money.
Well, I'm glad to hear somebody admit it.
Do you suppose you could
write a radio speech
that would put that fellow over?
- [Ann] Oh, I'm sure I can.
- Do it, and I'll give you $100 a week.
- $100--
- That's only the beginning.
You play your cards right
and you'll never have to
worry about money again.
Oh, I knew it.
- Hello.
Whenever there's a pretty woman around--
This is my nephew, Ted
Sheldon, Miss Mitchell.
- How do you do?
- All right, Casanova,
I'll give you a break.
See that Miss Mitchell gets
a car to take her home.
- Always reading my mind, aren't you?
- Thank you very much for everything.
- And, Miss Mitchell,
I think from now on you'd
better work directly with me.
- Yes, sir.
(upbeat orchestral music)
(typewriter keys clacking)
(groaning)
(orchestral music)
Hey!
I thought you were asleep.
- [Girl] We just wanted to say good night.
- [Girl] Goodnight sis.
(groaning)
- Oh, you little brats,
you're just stalling.
I said goodnight.
- Come, come, come, children.
It's past your bedtime.
Go on, go on.
(children fussing)
- Come on, pooch, come on.
- Come on, come on.
- [Woman] Now scooch off to bed.
- Stick a fork through me, I'm done.
I'll never get this speech right.
- Oh, yes you will, Ann, dear.
You're very clever.
- Yeah, I know.
What are you looking for?
- Your purse, I need $10.
- What for?
I gave you $50 just the other day.
- Yes, I know, dear, but Mrs.
Burke had her baby yesterday.
Nine pounds.
And there wasn't a thing in the house.
And then the Community Chest lady came--
- And 50's all gone, huh?
Who is the 10 for?
- The Websters.
- You remember, those lovely people
your father used to take care of?
I thought I'd buy them some groceries.
Oh, Ann, dear, it's a shame, those poor--
- You're marvelous, Ma.
You're just like Father used to be.
Do you realize a couple of weeks ago
we didn't have enough to eat ourselves?
- Well, yes, I know, dear, but
these people are in such need
and we have plenty now.
- If you're thinking of
that $1,000, forget it.
It's practically all gone.
We owed everybody in town.
Now, you just gotta stop
giving all your money away.
- Oh, Ann, dear.
- Oh, I'm sorry, Ma.
Oh, don't pay any attention to me.
I guess I'm just upset about all this.
Gee whiz, here I am with
a great opportunity to get somewhere,
to give us security for once
in our lives, and I'm stuck.
If I can put this over, your
Mrs. Burke can have six babies.
- You mean the speech you're writing?
- Yeah, I don't know, I
simply can't get it to gel.
I created somebody who was going
to give up his life for a principle.
Hundreds of thousands of people
are gonna listen to him over the radio.
And unless he says something that's,
well, that's sensational,
it's just no good.
- Well, honey, of course I don't know
what kind of a speech
you're trying to write,
but judging from the samples I've read,
I don't think anybody'll listen.
- What?
- Darling, there are so many
complaining political speeches.
People are tired of hearing
nothing but doom and despair on the radio.
If you're gonna have him say anything,
why don't you let him say
something simple and real,
something with hope in it?
If your father were alive,
he'd know what to say.
- Oh, yes.
Father certainly would.
- Wait a minute.
- Hmm?
- That's your father's diary, Ann.
- Father's--
I never knew he had a diary.
- There's enough in it for a 100 speeches,
things people ought to hear nowadays.
You'll be careful of it, won't you, dear?
Always helped to keep
your father alive for me.
- You bet I will, Ma.
(angry chattering)
- Wait a minute, John Doe
don't wanna sign no autographs.
- Well, what does he do all day?
- What does he do all day?
He's writing out his memories.
(angry chattering)
- Sorry, lady, you can't see Mr. Doe.
He wants to be alone.
No.
No, he just sits around all
day and commutes with himself.
("Take Me Out to the Ballgame")
Ball.
- I don't know how you're gonna stand it
around here till after Christmas.
I'll bet you ain't heard a
train whistle in two weeks.
- Strike.
- I know why you're hanging around.
You're stuck on the girl.
That's all a guy needs is to
get hooked up with a woman.
- What was that, a single?
- First baseman dropped the ball.
- Butterfingers.
Tough luck, pal.
- A guy has a woman on his
hands, first thing he knows,
his life is balled up
with a lot more things.
Furniture.
- Did you get him?
- You're out.
- Swell.
What's this, the end of the eighth?
- [John] Ninth.
- Hey, Beany, there's a couple
of lugs from the Chronicle
snooping around out here.
- Ah.
Come on, Angelface.
Gangway.
- What's the score, Angelface?
- Three to two, our favor.
- Gee, that's great.
- Hey, you got swell form there.
Must've been a pretty good pitcher.
- Pretty good, yeah.
I was just about ready
for the Major Leagues
when I chipped a bone in my elbow.
I got it pitching a 19 inning game.
- 19?
- Yep.
There was a Major League
scout there watching me, too.
And he came down after
the game with a contract.
But you know what?
I couldn't lift my arm to sign it.
I'll be okay though as
soon as I get it fixed up.
- That's too bad.
- What do you mean, too bad?
- Huh?
Oh, that you'll never
be able to play again.
- What are you talking about?
I just told you I was gonna get my--
- [Man] Well, you know
how they are in baseball
if a guy's mixed up in a racket.
- Racket, what do you mean?
- Well, I was just thinking
about this John Doe business.
Why, as soon as it comes
out it's all a fake,
you'll be washed up in
baseball, won't you?
- Yeah.
Doggone, I never thought about that.
("Funeral March" by Frederic
Chopin on harmonica)
Gosh.
- And another thing, what about
all the kids in the country,
the kids that idolize ballplayers?
What are they gonna think about you?
- Yeah.
Hey, Colonel.
(harmonica music)
Did you hear that?
I got to figure some
way out of this thing.
- The elevators are still running.
- I know one way you can do it.
- How?
- Well, when you get
up there on the radio,
all you have to do is say
the whole thing's a frame up.
Make you a hero, sure as you're born.
- Yeah, but how am I
going to get my arm fixed?
- That's a cinch.
I know somebody who'll give you $5,000
just to get up on the
radio and tell the truth.
- $5,000?
- Yeah, $5,000 and he gets it right away.
You don't have to wait till Christmas.
- Look out, Long John,
they're closing in on you.
- Say, who's putting up this dough?
- Fella runs the Chronicle.
Here's the speech you make
and it's all written for you.
- $5,000.
- [Man] It's on the level.
(upbeat orchestral music)
- No, I'm sorry, tickets for
the broadcast are all gone.
Phone the Bulletin.
- Sorry, no more tickets left.
(chattering)
- Here he is.
- [Ann] Hello John, all
set for the big night?
Swell.
- Turn around.
- One moment.
- Now stand still.
- Hold it, Mr. Doe.
Big smile, Mr. Doe.
Ah that's swell.
- Okay, Beany, that's all,
take them out will you?
- Alright, scram now.
- Come on.
Can't I get another picture?
- Now look John, here's the speech.
It's in caps and double spaced.
You won't have no trouble reading it.
Not nervous, are you?
- No.
- Of course not, he wouldn't be.
- Who?
- John Doe, the one in there.
- Hey don't let your knees rattle.
It picks up on the mic.
- Oh Beany.
You needn't be nervous, John
All you have to remember to be sincere.
- Pick up that phone Miss
Mitchell it's for you.
- [Ann] Okay.
Hello?
Yes, mother.
- Oh, thank you, darling.
Oh, there he is, the poor dear man.
Oh good luck to you, Mr. Doe.
We want you to know that
we're are all for you.
The girls all decided that
you're not to jump off any roof at all.
(chattering)
- You got the speech I gave you?
- Yeah.
- Now look, I'll give
the money to the Colonel
just as soon as you get started.
We'll have a car waiting at
the side entrance for you.
- Okay.
- How'd you get in here?
- Oh, I just came in to wish him luck.
- Come on, out, out.
Mother says good luck, too.
John, when you read the speech please,
please believe every word.
He turned out to be wonderful person John.
- Who?
- [Ann] John Doe, the one in the speech.
- Oh.
- [Ann] You know something?
I've actually fallen in love with him.
- All right, there he is, sister.
Now come, plenty of bulk.
- What's the idea?
- No, no, no, no, no that's too much.
That's not what, not so much, come on.
- [Man] That's it.
- Oh, this is no time for
cheap publicity, Mr. Connell.
- Listen if that guy lays an
egg I want something out of it.
I'm getting a Jane Doe ready.
- Ah come on, will you fellas?
Give me a chance, I have to--
- Just one more, will you please?
- Now that's fine honey, you go ahead.
After you.
You've got to be running, go ahead.
- How you doing?
- Alright Beany, bring them in.
- Holy smoke, a half a Heelot.
- There you are, boss,
just like you ordered.
Symbols of little people.
- Okay, get 'em up.
- Alright little fella.
- This is ridiculous, Mr. Connell.
Come on give me a chance.
The man's on the air in
only a few more minutes.
Oh, fellas I told you can have
all the pictures you want afterward.
No, come on, Ed.
And how about you?
Come on, come on, that's right.
Afterwards you can get
all the pictures you want.
- [Man] Oh I know but,
well thank you very much.
- Come on, will you?
That way, that's right.
- Come on Snooks.
You better bail out.
- Well, goodbye, Mr. Doe.
- Beany.
- Alright, alright.
- Better get ready, one minute to go.
- Wow, one minute to go and
the score's nothing to nothing.
Now please, John.
You won't let me down, will ya?
Will ya?
Of course you won't.
If you'll just think of
yourself as the real John Doe.
Listen, everything in that speech
are things a certain man believed in.
He was my father, John.
When he talked, people listened.
And they'll listen to you, too.
Funny, you know what my
mother said the other night?
She said to look into your eyes
and I'd see my father there.
- Hey what do you say?
- Okay, we're coming.
Come on.
Now listen, John, you're a pitcher.
Now get in there and pitch.
Good luck.
- [Beany] Give him room,
let him through, come on.
(chattering)
- Hey, let's get out of here.
There's the door right there.
- [Man] Hey what are you doing here?
- That's what I'd like to know.
- [Man] Come on, out, out.
- Hey, he's a friend of mine.
- Never mind, let him alone, he's alright.
I'll be right over there pulling for you.
John, over here.
- [Man] Stand by.
(applauding)
- Phone the Chronicle.
Tell 'em to start
getting those extras out.
(orchestral music)
- And good evening ladies and gentlemen,
this is Kenneth Fry speaking
for the New Bulletin.
Tonight we give you something
entirely new and different.
Standing beside me is the young man
who has declared publicly that
on Christmas Eve he
intends to commit suicide,
giving as his reason, quote,
I protest against the
state of civilization.
End quote.
Ladies and gentlemen, the
New Bulletin takes pleasure
in presenting the man who is fast becoming
the most talked about person
in the country, John Doe.
(orchestral music)
(applauding)
- Ladies and gentlemen.
I am the man you all know as John Doe.
I took that name because
it seems to describe--
Because it seems to describe
the average man, and that's me.
(clearing throat)
And that's me.
Well, it was me before I
said I was going to jump off
the City Hall roof at
midnight on Christmas Eve.
Now I guess I'm not average anymore.
Now I'm getting all sorts of
attention, from big shots too.
- We've been double crossed.
- We have?
- The Mayor and Governor, for instance,
they don't like those
articles I've been writing.
- You're an impostor, young fella.
That's a pack of lies you're telling.
Who wrote that speech for you?
(angry shouting)
- Beany, get that guy.
- [Man] A publicity
stunt for the Bulletin.
(angry shouting)
A publicity stunt for the Bulletin.
- Get him out.
- Spencer.
- [Radio announcer] Ladies and gentlemen,
the disturbance you just heard
was caused by someone in the audience
who tried to heckle Mr. Doe.
The speech will continue.
- Well, people like the Governor
people like the Governor--
people like the Governor and
that fella can stop worrying.
I'm not gonna talk about them.
I'm gonna talk about us, the
average guys, the John Does.
If anybody ever asked you what
the average John Doe is like,
you couldn't tell him because
he's a million and one things.
He's Mr. Big and Mr. Small.
He's simple and he's wise.
He's inherently honest,
but he's got a streak
of larceny in his heart.
He seldom walks up to a public
telephone without shoving
his finger in the slot to see
if somebody left a nickel there.
(laughing)
He's the man the ads are written for,
the fella everybody sells things to.
He's Joe Dokes, the
world's greatest stooge,
and the world's greatest strength.
Yes, sir.
Yes, sir, we're a great
family, the John Does.
We're the meek who are
supposed to inherit the earth.
You'll find us everywhere.
We raise the crops, we dig
the mines, work the factories,
keep the books, fly the
planes, and drive the buses.
And when a cop yells,
stand back there you,
he means us, the John Does.
- Well what kind of a speech is that?
Didn't you read it?
- We've existed since time began.
We built the Pyramids,
we saw Christ crucified,
pulled the oars for Roman emperors,
sailed the boats for Columbus,
retreated from Moscow with Napoleon,
and froze with Washington at Valley Forge.
Yes, sir, we've been in there
dodging left hooks since
before History began to walk.
In our struggle for freedom
we've hit the canvas many a time,
but we always bounce back because
we're the people and we're tough.
(applauding)
They've started a lot of talk
about free people going soft,
that we can't take it.
That's a lot of hooey.
The free people can beat the
world at anything from war
to tiddlywinks if we all
pull in the same direction.
(applauding)
I know a lot of you are
saying, what can I do?
I'm just a little punk.
I don't count.
Well you're dead wrong.
The little punks have always
counted because in the long run
the character of a
country is the sum total
of the character of it's little punks.
(applauding)
But we've all got to
get in there and pitch.
We can't win the ball game
unless we have team work,
and that's where every John Doe comes in.
It's up to him to get
together with his team mate,
and your team mate, my friends,
is the guy next door to you.
Your neighbor, he's a
terribly important guy,
that guy next door.
You're gonna need him
and he's gonna need you so look him up.
If he's sick, call on him.
If he's hungry, feed him.
If he's out of a job, find him one.
To most of you, your
neighbor is a stranger.
A guy with a barking dog
and a high fence around him.
Now you can't be a stranger
to any guy that's on your own team.
So tear down the fence that separates you.
Tear down the fence and you'll tear down
a lot of hates and prejudices.
Tear down all the fences in the country
and you'll really have teamwork.
(applauding)
I know a lot of you are
saying to yourselves,
he's asking for a miracle to happen.
He's expecting people to
change all of a sudden.
Well, you're wrong.
It's no miracle.
It's no miracle because I see it happen
once a year and so do
you, at Christmas time.
There's something swell about
the spirit of Christmas.
To see what it does to
people, all kinds of people.
Now why can't that spirit, that
same warm Christmas spirit,
last the whole year round?
Gosh.
If it ever did, if each and every John Doe
would make that spirit last
365 days out of the year
we'd develop such a strength,
we'd create such a tidal wave of goodwill
that no human force
could stand against it.
Yes sir, my friends,
the meek can only inherit
the Earth when the John Does
start loving their neighbors.
You better start right now.
Don't wait till the game is
called on account of darkness.
Wake up, John Doe, you're
the hope of the world.
- John, you were wonderful.
(applauding)
(cheering)
- Let's get out of here.
- Now you're talking.
(chattering)
Gangway, you Heelots.
Hey.
(sighing)
I knew you'd wake up sooner or later.
Boy, am I glad we got out of that mess.
- I had the 5,000 all sewed up.
Could've been on my way to old Doc Brown.
"You're a pitcher, John" she says.
"Now go in there and pitch."
What a sucker.
- She's a Heelot just like the rest.
Lucky you got away from her.
- What was I doing making
a speech, anyway, me, huh?
Jeez, the more I think
about it the more I could--
- Tear town all the fences.
Why, if you tore one picket off
your neighbor's fence, he'd sue you.
- 5,000, had it right in my hand.
- What do you mean he ran away?
Well go after him, find him.
That man is terrific.
(train whistling)
- And here we come.
(harmonica music)
(mimicking a musical instrument)
(train whistling)
(groovy music)
Jitterbugs.
Yeah.
- How much money we got left?
- Four bits.
- Better make it doughnuts, huh?
- Yeah.
(harmonica music)
- What'll it be, gents?
- Have you got a couple of steaks
about that big and that thick?
- [Colonel] Yeah, with hash
brown potatoes and tomatoes
and apple pie and ice cream and coffee?
- And doughnuts, I know.
Hey, Ma, sinkers, a pair.
- [Woman] Sinkers, a pair, comin' up.
- Glad he took the T out of that.
- Hey Look.
- [Colonel] Join the John Doe Club.
- [John] John Doe Club?
- Uh-oh.
- Are you John Doe?
- Who?
- John Doe.
- [Colonel] Ah, you need glasses, buddy.
- It's the spitting image of John Doe.
- Yeah, but his name's Willoughby.
- [John] I'm John Willoughby,
I'm a baseball player.
- Ah, no, I'd know that voice anywhere.
You can't kid me.
You're John Doe.
Ma!
Ma.
That's John Doe.
- John Doe?
- Yeah, sitting right there, big as life.
- Who'd you say it was?
- John Doe, the big guy there.
(frantic chattering)
That is John Doe.
Hey Operator, Dan Beaver.
Call everybody in town.
John Doe was just in my place.
Yeah, he ordered doughnuts.
- [Man] John Doe.
Let's see John Doe.
(horn honking)
- You're all here to see John
Doe and you're all neighbors,
but my office is packed
like a sardine box.
- [Woman] What does John
Doe look like, Mr. Mayor?
- Oh he's one of those
great, big, outdoor type men.
No you can't see him, you didn't
vote for me the last time.
Shame on you, what are you doing here?
Get off my front porch.
Mr. Norton come yet?
Well wonder where he
is, what's keeping him?
He should've been here 15 minutes ago.
There he comes now.
(sirens blaring)
Now everybody on your dignity.
Don't do anything to
disgrace our little town.
We gotta show off.
- Better let me talk to him.
- Alright, but present it to him
as a great cause for the common man.
- [Man] Ah here he comes.
Give him room down there, give him room.
Come on now.
- Here they come, here they come.
Here's Mr. Norton.
How do you do, Mr. Norton?
I'm Mayor Hawkins.
- The crowd back there.
- Let me go you darn fool.
I'm the Mayor.
Mr. Norton, Mr. Norton, Mr.
Norton, I'm Mayor Hawkins.
Your office telephoned me to hold him.
- Well that's fine, how is he?
- Oh he's fine, he's
right in my office there.
You know it's a big honor having
John Doe here, and you too.
Haven't had so much excitement
since the old City Hall burnt down.
People so excited, they
nearly tore his clothes off.
Oh Matilda, phone the newspapers.
Tell them Mr. Norton's here.
Step inside, Mr. Norton, to my office.
It's very comfortable Mr. Norton.
Just had it air-conditioned.
Gangway please, make room for Mr. Norton.
Gangway, gangway.
Here he is Mr. Norton, well taken care of.
The neighbors are serving
him a light lunch.
- Hello, John.
- Hello.
- Mr. Mayor, if you don't mind,
we'd like to talk to him alone.
- Why certainly, certainly.
Alright everybody clear out.
Everybody, quickly now.
Come on.
That's right, come on.
Don't argue with me here.
Wait till we get home.
- Don't you push me around like that
even though I am your wife.
- Look Mr. Norton, I think
you got a lot of nerve
having these people hold us here.
- There's nobody holding you here Mr. Doe.
It's only natural that--
- If there's nobody holding
us here let's get going.
Incidentally, my name
isn't Doe, it's Willoughby.
- Look, John.
Something important happened.
They're forming John Doe Clubs.
We know of eight already and they say--
- John Doe Clubs, what for?
- To carry out the principles
you talked about in your radio speech.
- I don't care what they're forming.
I'm on my way and I don't like
the idea of being stopped either.
- Oh, but you don't how big this thing is.
You should see the thousands of telegrams
we've received and what
they're saying about you.
- Look, it started as a
circulation stunt, didn't it?
Well you got your circulation.
Now why don't you let me alone?
- Oh it started as a circulation
stunt but it isn't anymore.
Mr. Norton wants to get in back of it
and sponsor clubs all over the country.
He wants to send you on a lecture tour.
- Me?
- Uh-huh.
- Certainly.
With your ability to influence people,
it might grow into a glorious movement.
- Then let's get something straight here.
I don't want any part of this.
If you got an idea I'm going around
lecturing to people why you're crazy.
Baseball's my racket
and I'm sticking to it.
Come on Colonel, let's get out of here.
- John--
- [Hawkins] Please, please
I just got rid of one crowd.
- But please, Mr. Mayor,
tell him the John Doe
Club wants to talk to him.
- Let them in, Mr.
Mayor, let them come in.
- Okay folks but remember your manners.
No stampeding.
Walk slow, like you do when
you come to pay your taxes.
- Okay.
All right, give me a chance.
- Come right in.
- My name's Bert Hansen, Mr. Doe.
I'm the head soda-jerker
at Schwabacher's drugstore.
Well, sir, you see me and my
wife, we heard your broadcast
and we got quite a bang out of it.
Especially my wife.
Kept me up half the night saying,
"that man's right, honey.
"Trouble with the world is
"nobody gives a hoot about his neighbor.
"That's why everybody in town
"is sore and cranky with each other."
I said, "that's fine,
"but how's a guy gonna go around lovin'
"the kind of neighbors we got?
"Old Sourpuss, for instance."
(laughing)
You see, Sourpuss Smithers
lives alone next door to us.
He's a cranky old man who runs
the second hand furniture store.
We haven't spoken to him for years.
I always figured he was
an ornery old gent that hated the world
'cause was always slamming his garage door
and playing the radio so loud
it kept half the neighbors up.
(laughing)
Well anyway, the next morning
I'm out watering the lawn
and I look over and there's Sourpuss
on the other side of the hedge
straightening out a dent in his fender.
And my wife yells to me out the window,
she says, "go on, speak to him, Bert."
I figured well heck I can't lose anything,
so I yelled over to him,
"good morning, Mr. Smithers."
He went right on pounding his fender.
Was I burned.
So I turned around to
give my wife a dirty look.
She said, "louder, he didn't hear you."
So in a voice you could've heard
in the next county I yelled,
"good morning, Mr. Smithers!"
(laughing)
Well sir, you could have
knocked me over with a feather.
Old Sourpuss turned
around, surprised like,
put on a big smile, came
over and took my hand
like an old lodge brother and
said, "good morning, Hansen.
"I've been wanting to
talk to you for years
"only I thought you didn't like me."
Then he started chatting
away like a happy little kid.
He got so excited his eyes--
Well, Mr. Doe before we got through
I found out Smithers is a swell
egg, only he's pretty deaf
and that accounts for all the noises.
He says it's a shame how little
we know about our neighbors.
And then he got an idea.
And he said, "how's about
inviting everybody some place
"where we can all get together
"and know each other a little better?"
Well I'm feeling so good by
this time I ripe for anything.
So Smithers goes around the neighborhood
inviting everybody to a
meeting at the schoolhouse.
And I tell everybody that comes
into the store, including
Mr. Schwabacher my boss.
I'm talking too much.
- Oh no.
(chattering)
- Well, I'll be doggone if
for 40 people don't show up.
Course, none of us knew what to do,
but we sure got a kick out
of seeing how glad everybody
was just to say hello to one another.
- Tell him about making
Sourpuss chairman, honey.
- Oh yeah, we made Sourpuss chairman
and decided to call
ourselves the John Doe Club.
Say, incidentally, this is my wife.
Come here, honey.
This is my wife, Mr. Doe.
- How do you do, Mr. Doe?
Sourpuss is here, too.
- [John] Oh, is he?
- This is Sourpuss, or excuse
me, Mr. Smithers, Mr. Doe.
- That's alright, if you
didn't call me Sourpuss,
it wouldn't feel natural.
(laughing)
- Well anyway, I guess nearly everybody
in the neighborhood came
except the Delaneys.
The Delaneys live in a big house
with an iron fence around it
and they always keep their blinds drawn.
And we always figured that he
was an old miser that sat back
counting his money, so why
bother about inviting him?
Until Grimes the milkman
spoke up and he said,
"say, you've got the Delaneys all wrong."
And then he tells us about
how they canceled their milk last week,
and he found it looked
kind of curious like
peeked in under the blinds
and found the house was empty.
"If you ask me", he
says, "they're starving."
- Old man Delaney's been bringing
his furniture over to my place at night,
one piece at a time and selling it.
- Well sir a half a dozen of
us went over there to fetch him
and we brought him to the meeting.
And what a reception they got.
Everybody shook hands with
them and made a fuss over them.
Well, finally Mr. and Mrs.
Delaney sat right down and cried.
- [Smithers] Then we started to find
out about a lot of other people.
- Yeah sure, well you know
Grubbel, for instance.
- Grubbel's here.
See?
- Yeah, that's him.
You don't know Grubbel, but he's the man
that everybody figured
was the worst no account
in the neighborhood because
he lived like a hermit.
Nobody would have anything to do with him
that is until Murphy the
postman told us the truth.
"Grubbel," he says, "he
lives out of garbage cans
"because he won't take charity.
"'Cause it'd ruin his
self respect" he says.
- Just like you said
on the radio, Mr. Doe.
- Well sir, about a dozen
families got together
and gave Grubbel a job
watering their lawns.
Isn't that wonderful?
And then we found jobs
for six other people
and they've all gone off relief.
- And my boss, Mr. Schwabacher,
made a job in his warehouse
for old man Delaney.
- And he gave you that $5 raise.
- Yeah, wasn't that swell?
- Why, Bert, I feel slighted.
I'd like to join, but nobody asked me.
- I'm sorry, Mayor, but we voted
that no politician could join.
- Just the John Does of the neighborhood.
You know how politicians are.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- Well the reason we wanted
to tell you this, Mr. Doe,
was to give you an idea
of what you started.
From where I'm sitting, I don't see
any sense in you jumping off any building.
- [Group] No, no.
- Well, thank you for listening.
Goodbye, Mr. Doe.
You're a wonderful man.
It strikes me you could be mighty useful
walking around for a while.
- Goodbye.
- Goodbye, Mr. Doe.
- I'm Mrs. Delaney, Mr. Doe.
God bless you, my boy.
- Gee wiz, I'm all mixed up.
I don't get it.
Look, all those swell people
think I'm gonna jump off
a building or something.
I never had any such idea.
Gosh.
A fella would have to be
a fine example himself
to go around telling other people how to--
Say look, what happened the other night
was on account of Miss Mitchell here.
She wrote the stuff.
- Don't you see what a
wonderful thing this can be?
But we need you, John.
- You're hooked.
I can see that right now, they got you.
Well, I'm through.
For three years I've
been trying to get you
up to the Columbia River country.
First it was your glass
arm, then it was the radio
and now it's the John Doe Clubs.
Well, I ain't waiting another minute.
(chattering)
Gangway, you heelots!
(gasping)
- Hey Colonel, wait a minute.
(chattering)
Hey, Colonel!
- I want you personally to go along
with John Doe and Miss Mitchell
and handle the press and the radio.
- Me?
- Yes.
I won't take any chances.
And Johnson.
- Yes, D.B.?
- Your crew will do the mop up job.
They'll follow John Doe into every town,
see that the clubs are properly organized
and the charters issued.
- Right.
- There are eight flags up there now.
I want to see that map
covered before we get through.
(upbeat orchestral music)
(cheering)
(upbeat acoustic music)
(applauding)
(parade music)
(cheering)
- This has grown like wildfire.
If they made demands I'd understand it,
but the John Does ask for nothing.
- People are going off relief.
If this keeps up, I'll be out of a job.
- As soon as he gets strong enough
we'll find out what he wants.
30 every Thursday, 60 at 60.
Who knows what?
- I'm sorry, boss, they just won't let
anybody talk politics
with him, it's crazy.
- We've got to get to them.
They represent millions of voters.
(applauding)
- I tell you ladies and gentlemen,
this thing has been nothing
short of a prairie fire.
We've received so many
applications for charters
for the John Doe clubs we haven't
been able to take care of them.
- [Man] I'd hate to have
that many pins stuck in me.
(laughing)
- This John Doe convention is a natural.
It's going to put our city on the map.
Why over 2,400 John Doe clubs
are sending delegates,
can you imagine that?
You Mr. Mayor will be the official host.
You will make the arrangements
for decorating the city,
parades and a reception for
John Doe when he gets home.
And don't wear your high hat.
- No high hat?
- No high hat.
And from you Connell I want a special
John Doe edition every day
until the convention is over.
And now please step into the outer office
and look your prettiest
because there are photographers there
to take pictures of this committee.
- [Man] Don't worry, D.B.,
everything will be taken care of.
- Sure.
- Isn't it all too wonderful?
(chattering)
- [Photographer] Oh Mr.
Mayor, would you sit down
in the front row please?
You ladies get close to him.
- Well, I don't get it.
- Get what?
- Look D.B. I'm supposed
to know my way around.
This John Doe movement's
cost you a fortune.
Now this convention is
going to cost plenty.
- Well?
- I'm stuck with two and two
and I'm a sucker if I
can make four out of it.
Where do you come in?
- I have the satisfaction of knowing
that my money has been
spent for a worthy cause.
- I see, I better stick
to running the paper.
- I think maybe you better had.
Connell, I'd like to have
the John Doe contract,
all of the receipts for the money
we advanced for the
letter Miss Mitchell wrote
for which I gave her a $1,000.
- Yes, sure.
- Well we leave for the
airport in half an hour.
Is that Johnny boy's room?
Better hustle him up.
- He'll be ready on
time, he's packing now.
- Ah good.
Did you see his picture
on the cover of Time?
- Yeah.
- I gotta give you credit, Annie girl.
I've handled a good many
big promotions in my time,
from the World's Fair
to a channel swimmer,
but this one has
certainly got me spinning.
And now, a John Doe convention.
Wow.
Hey, if you could only get him
to jump off City Hall
roof on Christmas Eve,
I'd guarantee you a half
a million people there.
- Charlie?
- Hmm?
- What do you make of him?
- Who, Johnny boy?
Well, I don't know what angle you want
but I'll give it to you quick.
Number one, he's got great yokel
appeal but he's a nice guy.
Number two, he's beginning
to believe he really wrote
that original suicide
letter that you made up.
Number three, he thinks you're
Joan of Arc or something.
- Yeah I know.
- [Charlie] Number four, well,
you know what number four is.
He's nuts about you.
Yeah it's running out of his ears.
- You left out number five.
We're all heels, me especially.
- [Charlie] Holy smoke.
- Come in.
- [John] I'm all packed.
- Good, I'll go and get Beany boy.
- Okay, Charlie boy.
(laughing)
Do you care if I sit down, out here?
- [Ann] No.
- You know, I had a
crazy dream last night.
It was about you.
- About me?
- Sure was crazy.
I dreamt I was your father.
There was something I was
trying to stop you from doing.
So, I got up out of
bed, and I walked right
through the wall here, right
straight into your room.
You know how dreams are.
And there you were in bed,
but you were a little girl,
you know about 10 and very pretty, too.
So I shook you and the moment you opened
your eyes, you hopped out of bed
and started running like the devil.
In your nightgown.
You ran right out the window there
and you ran over the tops of buildings
and roofs and everything for
miles and I was chasing you.
And all the time you were running,
you kept growing bigger
and bigger and bigger.
And pretty soon you were as big
as you are now, you know, grown up?
And all the time I kept asking myself,
what am I chasing her for?
And I didn't know.
Isn't that a hot one?
Well anyway, you ran into some place
and then I ran in after you.
And when I got there there
you were getting married.
The nightgown had changed
into a beautiful wedding gown.
You sure looked pretty, too.
And then I knew what I was
trying to stop you from doing.
Dreams are sure crazy, aren't they?
Well, would you like to know
who it was you were marrying?
- Oh, a tall handsome Ubangi, I suppose.
- [John] No, not that bad.
It was the fella that sends
you flowers every day.
Yeah, what's his name?
Mr. Norton's nephew?
- Ted Sheldon.
- Yeah, that's the one.
- But here's the funniest part of it all.
I was the fella up there
doing the marrying.
You know, the Justice of
the Peace or something.
- You were?
I thought you were chasing me.
- Well, yes I was, but I was
your father then you see?
But the real me, John Doe,
that is Long John Willoughby,
I was the fella with a book.
You know what I mean?
- I guess so.
Then what happened?
- Well I took you across my
knee and I started spanking you.
That is, I didn't do
it, I mean I did do it.
But it wasn't me, see,
I was your father then.
Well I had you across my knee and I said,
"Annie, I won't allow you to
marry a man that's just rich
"or that has his secretary
send you flowers.
"The man you marry has got
to swim rivers for you,
"he's got to climb high mountains for you,
"he's got to slay dragons for you.
"He's got to perform
wonderful deeds for you."
Yes sir, and all the time,
the guy up there you
know with the book, me,
just stood there noddin'
his head and he said,
"go to it Pop, whack her one for me
"because that's the way
I feel about it too."
So he says, "come down
and whack her yourself."
So I came down and I
whacked you a good one, see?
The he whacked you and I
whacked you another one.
We both started whacking you like--
- Well if you're through whacking her
come on let's get going.
Okay fellas, right in here.
You go out the side entrance.
There's a bunch of
autograph seekers out front.
We'll be down with the bags in a minute.
Come on, don't make a
Government project out of this.
Hi, Beany.
- When's our plane take off again?
- Couple of minutes.
- How many people do you
think we've talked to already,
outside the radio, I mean?
- Oh, I don't know, about 300,000.
- 300,000.
What makes them do it, Ann?
What makes them come and listen
and get up their John Doe
Clubs the way they do?
I've been trying to figure it out.
- Look, John, what we're
handing them are platitudes
things they've heard a million times.
Love thy neighbor, clouds
have silver linings,
turn the other cheek.
It's just--
- Yeah I heard 'em a million times too,
but they are, maybe they're like me,
just beginning to get an
idea what those things mean.
I never really thought
much about people before.
They were always just somebody
to fill up the bleachers.
Only time I worried
about them is if they--
is when they didn't see me pitch.
You know, lately I've been
watching them when I talk to them.
I see something in their faces.
I could feel that they
were hungry for something.
You know what I mean?
Maybe that's why they came.
Maybe they're just lonely
and wanted somebody to say hello to.
I know how they feel.
I've been lonely and hungry for something
practically all my life.
- [Man] All aboard, folks.
- We'll have the city behind us.
- Yeah, that's true.
Oh, somebody else sitting here?
- No, that's your seat.
- And this is your coat.
- Mine?
- A little token of appreciation.
- Oh.
Oh, it's beautiful, D.B.
Well, I don't quite know what to say.
- Oh don't say anything
at all, just sit down.
- Go ahead and open it, open it.
- Oh.
Oh it's lovely.
- And a new contract goes with it.
- Well, come on spring it.
You've got something on your mind.
Must be stupendous.
(laughing)
- You know that's what I like about her.
Right to the point like that.
Alright practical Annie, here it is.
Tomorrow night, before
a crowd of 15,000 people
and talking over a
nationwide radio hook-up,
John Doe will announce the
formation of a third party.
- A third party?
- Yes, the John Doe Party,
devoted entirely to the interests
of all the John Does all over the country.
Which practically means 90% of the voters.
He will also announce the third party's
candidate for the presidency.
A man who he personally recommends.
A great humanitarian.
The best friend the John Does have.
- Mr. D.B. Norton.
- Yes.
- Wow.
♪ Glory, glory, hallelujah ♪
♪ His truth is marching on ♪
(cheering)
- [Radio Broadcaster]
And although the opening
of the convention is
hours off the delegates
are already pouring into
the ball park by the droves
with lunch baskets, banners
and petitions asking John Doe
not to jump off any roof.
- [Radio Broadcaster] No
matter how you look at it,
it's still a phenomenal movement.
These John Does or the hoy polloi,
as you've heard people call them,
have been laughed at and ridiculed,
but here they are gay and happy,
having traveled 1,000s of
miles, their expenses paid
by their neighbors to come to pay homage
to their hero John Doe.
- And in these days of wars and bombings,
it's a hopeful sign that a simple idea
like this can sweep the country.
An idea based on friendliness,
on giving and not taking,
on helping your neighbor and
asking nothing in return.
And if a thing like this can happen,
don't let any of your grumbling friends
tell you that humanity is falling apart.
This is John B. Hughes signing off now,
returning you to our main studio
until nine o'clock when the
convention will officially open.
- [Woman] Oh, John, come in.
- Say, I'm kind of...
It's raining out a little.
- That's all right.
It's good to see you, sit down.
- Thanks.
It's for Ann.
- [Woman] Oh how nice,
thank you very much.
- Flowers.
- I'm terribly sorry she isn't here.
- She isn't?
- No, she just left, I'm
surprised you didn't run into her.
She went over to Mr. Norton's house.
- Oh.
- Did you want to see her
about something important?
- Yeah, well, no, it'll wait.
Say he's a nice man, isn't he?
Mr. Norton, I mean.
He's done a lot for the...
Say, my coat's pretty wet.
I'm afraid I might have
wet the couch a little.
I'll I guess I'll see her
at the convention later.
- Yes of course, I'll see
that she gets the flowers.
- Thanks.
Good night, Mrs. Mitchell.
- Good night, John.
- Say Mrs. Mitchell I'm
kind of glad Ann isn't here.
You see, I came over here
hoping to see her alone
and kind of hoping I wouldn't
too you know what I mean?
There was something I
wanted to talk to her about.
Well it can wait, I guess.
- Good night.
- Good night, John.
- Say look Mrs. Mitchell,
have you ever been married?
Well, sure you have, gosh.
That's pretty silly.
Well I guess you must
think I'm kind of batty.
Well I guess I better be going at that.
- John, my husband said,
"I love you, will you marry me?"
- He did?
- What happened?
- I married him.
- Yeah, that's what I mean, see?
It was easy as all that, huh?
Yeah, but look Mrs. Mitchell.
You know I love Ann, and
it's gonna be awfully hard
for me to say it 'cause well
you know she's so wonderful
and well the best I ever was
was a bush league pitcher.
And you know I think she's in love
with another man, the one she made up.
You know, the real John Doe.
Well that's pretty tough competition.
I bet he'd know how to say it alright.
But me, I get up to it and
around and in back of it,
but I never get right to it.
You know what I mean?
So the only chance I've got is,
well, if somebody could
kind of give her a warning.
Sort of prepare her for the shock?
- You mean you'd like me to do it?
- Well, I was thinking,
yeah sort of break the ice.
- Of course I will, John.
- Thank you, Mrs. Mitchell.
Hey, you're okay.
- This John Doe meeting is gonna
be one of the biggest
things ever happened.
- Is that so?
- Why they're coming from all
over, trains, boxcars, wagons.
Look out!
- Hello, bodyguards, hey
have your dinner yet?
- Not yet.
- Oh that's all right.
- No, go and have dinner.
- Wait a minute, John.
- Hello, Mr. Connell.
- How are you, John?
John, I want to have a
little talk with you.
What's the matter?
Are you falling?
Come on.
- Hey, Boss.
- Oh, quiet, quiet, quiet.
So tell me something, did you read
the speech you're going to make tonight?
- No, I never read the
speeches before I make them.
I get more of a kick out of it that way.
- Uh-huh, it's just
exactly what I thought.
Beany, go on down to the office,
tell Pop to give you the speech.
There's a copy on my desk.
- Gee wiz boss, you know Mr. Norton
told me not to leave
him, even for a minute.
- Go on, go on, go on.
We'll be at Jim's Bar, up the street.
You're a nice guy, John.
I like you, you're gentle.
I always like gentle people.
Me, I'm hard.
Hard and tough.
I got no use for hard people.
Gotta be gentle to suit me.
Like you, for instance.
Yep, I'm hard.
But you want to know something?
I've got a weakness.
You'd never guess that would you?
Well, I have.
Wanna know what it is?
The Star Spangled Banner.
Screwy, huh?
Maybe it is.
Play The Star Spangled Banner
and I'm a sucker for it.
Always gets me right here.
You know what I mean?
- Yeah, it gets me right back here.
- Oh, back there, huh?
Well, every man to his own taste.
You weren't old enough for
the world war were you then?
No, no of course not.
You must have been just a kid.
I was.
I was just ripe and raring to go.
Know what my old man did when I joined up?
He joined up too.
Got to be a sergeant.
And here's a kick for you.
We were in the same outfit.
Funny, huh?
He was killed, John.
I saw him get it.
I was right there and
saw it with my own eyes.
Me, I came out without a scratch.
That is, excepting my ulcers.
I should be drinking milk,
you know this stuff is poison.
Hey, Jimmy.
- [Jim] Yes, Mr. Connell?
- What do you say, huh?
- All right.
- Yep, I'm a sucker for this country.
I'm a sucker for The Star Spangled Banner
and I'm a sucker for this country.
I like what we got here.
I like it.
A guy can say what he wants
and do what he wants without
having a bayonet shoved through his belly.
And that's all right.
- You betcha.
- Yeah.
And we don't anybody coming
around changing that, do we?
- No, sir.
When they do, I get
mad, I get boiling mad.
Right now, I'm sizzling.
I get mad for a lot of
other guys besides myself.
I get mad for a guy named Washington.
And a guy named Jefferson and Lincoln.
Lighthouses, John.
Lighthouses in a foggy world.
You know what I mean?
- Yeah, you bet.
- Listen, pal.
This fifth column stuff is
pretty rotten, isn't it?
- Yeah, it certainly is.
- And you'd feel like an awful sucker
if you found yourself marching
right in the middle of it, wouldn't you?
You, of course you wouldn't
know it because you're gentle.
But that's what you're doing.
You're mixed up with a skunk, my boy.
A no good, dangerous skunk.
- You're not talking
about Mr. Norton are you?
- I'm not talking about his
grandfather's pet poodle.
- You must be wrong, Mr. Connell.
He's been marvelous
about the John Doe Clubs.
- Yeah. (laughing)
Say, you're sold on this John Doe idea?
- Sure.
- Yeah sure, I don't blame you, sure.
It's a beautiful miracle, a
miracle that can only happen
right here in the good old
USA, and I think it's terrific.
What do you think of that?
Me, hard-boiled Connell, and
I think it's plenty terrific.
Alright.
Now supposing a certain
unmentionable worm,
who's initials are D.B.,
was trying to use that to shove
his way into the White House.
So he could put the screws on.
So he could turn out the
lights in those lighthouses.
What would you say about that?
- Nobody's gonna do that Mr. Connell.
They can't use the John
Doe Clubs for politics.
That's the main idea.
- Is that so?
Then what's a big political boss
like Hammett doing in town?
And a labor leader like Bennett.
And lots of other big shots that
are up at D.B.'s house right now.
Wolves, John, wolves.
Waiting to cut up the John Does.
Wait till you get a gander
at that speech you're gonna make tonight.
- You're all wet.
Miss Mitchell writes those speeches
and nobody can make her
write that kind of stuff.
- They can't huh?
Who do you think writes 'em, my aunt Emma?
I know she writes them and gets
a big bonus for doing them, too.
A mink coat and diamond bracelet.
Don't write 'em?
Why that gold-grabbing dame
would double cross her own mother
for a handful of Chinese yams.
- Shut up.
If you weren't drunk, I'd--
- Hey, Boss.
Here's the speech, Boss.
Hey.
- Go on and read it John,
and then start sockin'.
- Hey wait a minute, Mr. Doe.
- Jimmy.
- Yes, sir.
- Better bring me a glass of milk.
I'm smoking too much.
- Yes, Charlie, everything all set?
Fine.
John Doe been take care of?
Good.
How many people will be there, 15,000?
Oh my, that's fine.
Now listen, Charlie.
As soon as John Doe stops talking about me
I want you to start that demonstration,
and make it a big one you understand?
- Don't worry about that,
D.B. my boys are there.
They'll take care of it.
- What?
Yes, I'll be there 15 minutes
after I get your call.
- [Man] Why, Mr. Doe.
- Where are they?
- In the dining room, sir.
- Gentlemen, I think we're about
ready to throw that great big bombshell.
- [Man] Yeah, it's about time.
Even a conservative estimate shows
that we can count on anywhere between 10
and 20 million John Doe votes.
Add that to the labor vote
that Mr. Bennett will throw in.
And the votes controlled by Mr. Hammett
and the rest of you gentlemen
in your own territories
and nothing can stop us.
- As I said before, I'm with you,
providing you can guarantee
the John Doe vote.
- [D.B] Don't worry about that.
- You can count on me, on one condition.
Little Bennett's gotta be taken care of.
- [D.B.] Didn't I tell you that everybody
in this room would be taken care of?
My agreement with you gentlemen stands.
- I'm with you, D.B., but I still think
it's a very daring thing we're attempting.
- These are daring times, Mr. Barrington.
We're coming to a new order of things.
There's too much talk been
going in this country.
- That's right.
- [D.B] Too many
concessions have been made.
- [Man] True.
- What the American people
need is an iron hand.
- You're right D.B.
- That's true.
- You're quite right, D.B.
Quite right.
- Discipline.
And now may I offer a little
toast to Miss Ann Mitchell,
the brilliant and beautiful lady
who is responsible for all this.
- [Everyone] Miss Mitchell.
- Mr. Norton, I'd like to talk
to you alone for a minute.
- Oh, Miss Mitchell has
something to say to us.
- Speech, speech.
- Hello.
- John, I'm so glad to see you.
I was terribly worried.
- Did you write this?
- Yes I did, John, but I had
no idea what was going on.
- You didn't?
- No.
- That's a swell bracelet you're wearing.
- John, why aren't you at the convention?
Is there anything wrong?
- No, no, nothing's wrong.
Everything's fine.
So there's going to be a
new order of things, huh?
Everybody's gonna cut himself
a nice fat slice of the John Does eh?
You forgot one detail, Mr. Big Shot.
You forgot me, the prize
stooge of the world.
Why if you or anybody thinks
he's gonna use the John Doe Clubs
for his own rotten purpose
he's going to have to
do it over my dead body.
- Now hold on a minute, young man.
Hold on, that's rather big talk.
I started the John Doe Clubs with my money
and I'll decide whether or not
they're being properly used.
- No, you won't.
You're through deciding anything.
And what's more, I'm going
down to that convention
and I'm gonna tell those
people exactly what you
and all your fine feathered friends here
are trying to cook up for them.
And I'm gonna say it in
my own words this time.
- Stop him D.B.
(angry chattering)
- [Man] He'll ruin us, D.B..
- Wait a minute, wait a minute fella.
My uncle wants to talk to you.
- Listen to me, my son.
Before you lose your head completely,
may I remind you that I picked
you up out of the gutter,
and I can throw you
right back there again.
You've got a nerve
accusing people of things.
These gentlemen and I know what's best
for the John Does of America
regardless of what tramps like you think.
Get off that righteous horse of yours
and come to your senses.
You're the fake.
We believe in what we're doing.
You're the one that was paid
the 30 pieces of silver.
Have you forgotten that?
Well, I haven't.
You're a fake, John
Doe, and I can prove it.
You're the big hero that's supposed
to jump off tall buildings and things?
You remember?
What do you suppose
your precious John Does
will say when they find out that you never
had any intention of doing it?
That you were paid to say so?
You're lucky they don't
run you out of the country.
With the newspapers and the radio stations
that these gentlemen control,
we can kill the John Doe
movement deader than a doornail.
We'll do it too the moment
you step out of line.
Now if you still want
to go that convention
and shoot your trap off,
you go ahead and do it.
- You mean, you'd try to
kill the John Doe movement
if you can't use it to get what you want?
- [D.B.] You bet your
bottom dollar we would.
- Well that certainly is a new low.
I guess I've seen everything now.
You sit there back with your big cigars
and think of deliberately killing
an idea that's made millions
of people a little bit happier.
An idea that's brought thousands of them
here from all over the country.
By bus, and by freight
and jalopy and on foot
so they can pass on to each other
their own simple little experiences.
Why look, I'm just a mug and I know it,
but I'm beginning to
understand a lot of things.
Why your types are as old as history.
If you can't lay your dirty
fingers on a decent idea,
and twist it and squeeze it and stuff it
into your pocket you
slap it down like dogs,
if you can't eat it, you bury it.
Why this is the one worthwhile
thing that's come along.
People are finally finding out
that the guy next door isn't a bad egg.
That's simple, isn't it?
And yet a thing like that
has got a chance of spreading
till it touches last doggone
human being in the world,
and you talk about killing it.
Well, when this fire dies
down, what's going to be left?
More misery, more hunger and more hate.
And what's to prevent that
from starting all over again?
Nobody knows the answer to
that one and certainly not you,
with those slimy, bollixed
up theories you got.
The John Doe idea may
be the answer though.
It may be the one thing capable
of saving this cockeyed world,
yet you sit back there on your fat hulks
and tell me you'll kill
it if you can't use it.
Well, go ahead and try!
You couldn't do it in a
million years with all your
radio stations and all your
power because it's bigger than
whether I'm a fake, it's
bigger than your ambitions
and bigger than all the bracelets
and fur coats in the world.
- You bet it is, John!
- And that's exactly what I'm going
down there to tell those people.
(applauding)
- I'm gonna, you ungrateful rat.
My uncle's been too good to--
(thumping)
(suspenseful music)
- He's getting away.
(whistle blowing)
- John!
- Get me the Bulletin.
- John.
- I told you, D.B., you're
playing with dynamite.
- Don't let that girl get away.
- Before he gets through
tonight, he'll ruin us all.
I'll stop him, I'll stop him cold.
Don't worry, I've been ready for this.
- John.
Oh John, please listen to me.
Please I can explain everything John.
I didn't know what they were going to do.
Let me go with you John.
John, please.
- Go ahead, driver, ball park.
- Let me explain it to you John.
Please let me go with you.
Please, John.
- Mr. Norton wants to see you.
- Listen to me, Mayor I
want you to do as I say.
I want them both arrested.
You tell the police
department to pick up Connell.
I've got the girl here.
- I've got the Bulletin.
- I don't care what you charge them with.
If you're worried let
them go in the morning,
but keep them in jail overnight.
Hello, Bulletin?
Put Buck Meyer on.
♪ With my banjo on my knee ♪
♪ I'm going to Louisiana ♪
♪ My true love for to see ♪
♪ It rained all night the day I left ♪
♪ The weather it was dry ♪
♪ The sun so hot I froze to death ♪
♪ Susanna, don't you cry ♪
♪ Oh Susanna, oh don't you cry for me ♪
♪ I've come from Alabama
with my banjo on my knee ♪
♪ Oh Susanna, oh don't you cry for me ♪
♪ I've come from Alabama
with my banjo on my knee ♪
♪ I came from Alabama
♪ I'm going to Louisiana,
my true love for to see ♪
♪ It rained all night the day I left ♪
(cheering)
- Three cheers for John Doe.
- [Crowd] Hurray, hurray, hurray.
♪ My country 'tis of thee ♪
♪ Sweet land of liberty of thee I sing ♪
♪ Land where my fathers died ♪
♪ Land of the pilgrims' pride ♪
♪ From every mountainside
let freedom ring ♪
(cheering)
- Ladies and gentlemen.
- One moment, John.
We'll begin with a soft prayer.
Quiet, please.
Ladies and gentlemen, let's have a moment
of silent prayer for the John Does
all over the world, many of
whom are homeless and hungry.
Rise, please.
Everybody rise.
(frantic chattering)
- [Radio Broadcaster] News boys, hundreds
of yelling news boys are swarming
into the crowd like locusts.
- [Man] They're yelling John Doe's a fake.
- Fake?
(angry chattering)
- [Newspaper Boys] John Doe's a fake!
- Federal investigation
urged by Chamber of Commerce.
- How could he be a fake?
- It must be some kind of a gag.
- A what?
- A gag, a gag.
(whistle blowing)
(sirens blaring)
- Come on, come on step on it.
Step on it, step on it.
You all know you're places
now so let's get going.
Wait for the signal.
- Hey mister will you
autograph my balloon?
- Sure.
(frantic chattering)
- Ladies and gentlemen,
this is exactly what
I came down here to
tell you about tonight.
Please, if you all would just
be quiet for a few minutes,
I can explain this whole thing to you.
As you all know, this paper is published
by a man by the name of D.B. Norton.
- [Man] Get back, you.
- Everybody, wait a minute.
Wait a minute ladies and
gentlemen, my name is D.B. Norton.
You all know me.
I accuse this man of being a faker.
We've been taken for a lot of suckers
and I'm the biggest of the lot.
I spent a fortune backing this man
in what I believed to be a sincere
and worthy cause just as you all did
and now I find out it's
nothing but a cheap racket,
cooked up by him and two of my employees
for the sole purpose of collecting dues
from John Does all over the country.
- That's a lie!
- It's not a lie.
Nickel and dimes to stuff
into their own pockets.
You can read all about it
in the newspapers there.
- That's a lie, listen--
- Let go of me.
- Don't believe--
- This man had no intention of jumping off
the the top of a building.
He was paid to say so.
Do you deny that?
- That's got nothing to do with it.
- Were you paid or weren't you?
- Yes, I was paid, but--
- And what about the suicide note.
You didn't write that either.
- What difference does that make?
- Did you write it or didn't you?
- No, I didn't I didn't write it.
- You bet your life you didn't.
You look in your papers
ladies and gentlemen
and find you'll find Miss Mitchell's
signed confession that she
was the one who wrote it.
- Listen folks it's a fact that
I didn't write the letter--
- Now you see, he admits it.
You're a fake, John Doe.
And for what you have done to
all these people good people
they ought to run you out of the country.
And I hope they do it.
- [Man] Speak up, John, we believe you.
- Please listen, folks.
Now that he's through
shooting off his face,
I got couple of things to tell you about.
- Come on, the rest of
you get in here and riot.
Break this crowd up, come on.
- I'm sorry folks, but we
can't hear him anymore.
Something's gone wrong
with the loudspeakers.
- Doe's a fake.
Boo!
- Please, they can't hear me.
- Boo!
(yelling)
- This thing's not working.
Ladies and gentlemen.
(booing)
(yelling)
This thing's bigger
than whether I'm a fake.
Look Bert, you believe me, don't ya?
- Sure, I believe you.
Walking my legs off picking up
5,000 signatures for a phony.
There you are, Mr. Doe.
5,000 names asking you
not to jump off any roof.
- Makes no difference, Bert.
The idea's still good.
We don't have to give up our club.
- Yeah, well you can have it.
(shouting)
- They're starting to throw things.
Somebody's going to get hurt.
I'm afraid it will be John Doe.
Listen to that mob.
(shouting)
- I've got to go to him.
- Sorry, lady, I can't let you out.
- Let me go.
Oh please, please let me go.
They're crucifying him.
I can help him.
- [Man] Sorry sister, we
got orders to hold you.
- Orders from who?
Can't you see it's a frame up?
- Ann darling.
- [Ann] Oh Mother, they won't let me go.
They won't let me go.
(shouting)
- Listen, folks.
You gotta--
- Back to the jungle you hobo.
- Just another racket.
- Stick to your clubs.
- We've been fed baloney so
long we're getting used to it.
(shouting)
- The idea is still good.
Believe me, folks.
Listen John Does were
the hope of the world.
(angry shouting)
- [Radio Broadcaster]
They just finally managed
to get him out of the park.
And if that boy isn't
hurt it'll be a miracle.
Ladies and gentlemen this certainly looks
like the end of the John Doe movement.
- Well, boys, chalk up another
one to the Pontius Pilates.
- I should have been there.
I could have helped him.
He was so all alone.
- A lot of us are going to be mighty
ashamed of ourselves after tonight.
We certainly didn't give
that man much of a chance.
- [Colonel] Want sore coffee, Long John?
- No thanks, Colonel.
(dramatic orchestral music)
- Fake.
- Racketeer.
- Liar.
- Cheat.
- Impostor.
- Why don't you jump?
- Christmas Eve midnight. (laughing)
- Goodbye, Mr. Doe.
You're a wonderful man.
- And God bless you, my boy.
- Now get in there and pitch.
- You're a fake John
Doe and I can prove it.
You're the big hero that's meant to jump
off tall buildings and
things, do you remember?
What do you suppose your precious
John Does will say when they find out
that you never had any
intention of doing it?
That you were paid to say so?
- [Ann] Christmas Eve,
at midnight. (laughing)
♪ Silent night, holy night ♪
♪ Shepherds quake at the sight ♪
♪ Glories stream from heaven afar ♪
- Merry Christmas.
♪ Christ, the Savior is born ♪
(chattering)
- [Carolers] Merry Christmas.
- Who, John Doe?
Is that screwball still around?
- That dame's been calling all day.
- Sure, sure, I know.
Yeah, at midnight, huh? (laughing)
Okay, lady, we'll have the
place surrounded with nets.
- They're laughing at me.
- [Man] You're a sick girl, Ann.
You better take it easy.
- Who are you calling now?
You called that number,
not 10 minutes ago.
- Hello. Mr. Connell.
Have you seen him yet?
- Now listen, Ann, he can't possibly
get in without our seeing him.
I'm watching the side door
and the Colonel's out
front so stop worrying.
- Oh, thank you.
- Why Ann.
- Ann, don't be foolish.
- If this isn't the
craziest, the battiest,
the looniest wild goose
chase I ever heard of.
- Oh shut up, Bert.
Sourpuss is right.
- Yeah well if he is, I'm a banana split.
- That man's gonna be on that roof.
Don't ask me how I know I just know
and you know it as well as you do.
- Sure, sure I'd like to
believe in fairy tales,
but a guy that's a fake isn't
gonna jump off any roof.
- I don't think he was a fake.
Not with that face.
At any rate what he
stood for wasn't a fake.
- Okay, honey, okay.
(humming musically)
- Elevators ain't runnin'.
- Colonel.
- [Colonel] You should've
got out of bed Miss.
- Has he been here?
- No.
- Have you seen him?
- Haven't seen him for a week.
- Where's Connell?
- He's watching the other door.
- Oh, you're swell.
Oh.
- No sense in going up there.
I've been here for hours.
He ain't here.
- [Ann] Let me go, will ya?
- Now that's crazy, it's 14 floors.
- It's as far as the elevator goes.
We gotta walk up to the tower.
- That tramp is probably
full of Christmas cheer
and asleep in some flophouse.
- [Man] Let's go, I've
got to decorate my tree.
(bells chiming)
- [Man] Well, I give up.
I don't what gave us the idea
he'd attempt anything like this.
- [Man] I guess you're right.
I'm afraid the joke's on us, let's go.
- I hope nobody finds out we've been here.
I wouldn't do that if I were you John.
It'll do you no good.
The Mayor has policemen
downstairs with instructions
to remove all marks of identification
you have on your person.
You'll be buried in Potter's Field
and you'll have accomplished nothing.
- I've taken care of that.
I've already mailed a copy of
this letter to Mr. Connell.
- John, why don't you
forget this foolishness?
- Stop right where you are, Mr. Norton,
if you don't want to go overboard with me.
I'm glad you gentlemen are here.
You killed the John
Doe movement all right,
but you're gonna see
it born all over again.
Now take a good look, Mr. Norton.
- John!
John.
Oh John, don't do it.
I love you, I love you darling.
Oh please.
Please don't give up.
We'll start all over again.
Just you and I, it isn't too late.
The John Doe movement isn't dead yet.
You see John it isn't dead
or they wouldn't be here.
It's alive in them.
They kept it alive by being afraid of it.
That's why they came up here.
Oh, darling.
Sure it should have been killed.
It was dishonest.
But we can start clean now.
Just you and I.
It'll grow, John, and it'll grow big
because it'll be honest this time.
Oh John, if it's worth dying
for, it's worth living for.
Oh please, John.
Oh.
Oh please.
Please God, help me.
John.
John, look at me.
You want to be honest, don't you?
Well you don't have to die to
keep the John Doe idea alive.
Someone already died for that once.
The first John Doe.
And he's kept that idea
alive for nearly 2,000 years.
It was he who kept it alive
in them and he'll go on
keeping it alive forever and always.
For every John Doe movement these men kill
a new one will be born.
That's why those bells are ringing John.
They're calling to us.
Not to give up, but to keep on fighting,
to keep on pitching.
Oh don't you see, darling?
This is no time to give up.
You and I John, we...
Oh no.
No, John, if you die, I want to die, too.
Oh.
Oh, I love you. (crying)
Oh John.
- Mr. Doe, you don't have to...
We're with you, Mr. Doe.
We just lost our heads
and acted like a mob.
- What Bert's trying to say
is that we need you Mr. Doe.
There were a lot of us that
didn't believe what that man said.
We were going to start up our
John Doe Club again,
whether we saw you or not.
Weren't we, Bert?
And there were a lot of others
that were gonna do the same thing.
Well, Mr. Sourpuss even got
a letter from his cousin in Toledo--
- [Smithers] I got it right here, Mr. Doe.
- Only, it'd be a lot easier with you.
Please.
Please come with us, Mr. Doe.
(upbeat orchestral music)
- Long John.
- Mr. Doe.
Here we'll help you with her.
She'll be all right.
- [Man] We'll take her down to the car.
We gotta car right back down there.
- There you are, Norton, the
people, try and lick that.
(upbeat dramatic music)